Inventory of the F. Bruce Lamb papers, 1930-1994
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
F. Bruce Lamb papers
1930-1994
Lamb, F. Bruce (Frank Bruce), 1913-
03754
21.80 cubic ft. (24 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Personal papers of F. Bruce Lamb (1913-1992) a tropical forestry expert and writer; The collection contains his work as a professional forester, and his books on Manuel Cordova-Rios, an Amazon medicine man, and Harvey Logan, alias Kid Curry, and the Wild Bunch.
Biography of F. Bruce Lamb
F. Bruce Lamb (1913-1992) was a tropical forestry expert and writer. A graduate of the University of Michigan, School of Forestry, he wrote his doctoral dissertation on mahogany. During WWII Lamb traveled to Brazil as part of the Rubber Development Corporation in an effort by the United States to develop a rubber production program. After the war, his work as a consultant and with multiple forestry agencies, and eventually his employment with U.S. Plywood Corporation lead him to work throughout South America, Southeast Asia and parts of Africa. While working in the Amazon, Lamb met Manuel Cordova-Rios, who studied Amazonian medicinal plants under a Huni Kui (Cashinawa) shaman. Lamb wrote several books on the life and work of Cordova-Rios. In addition to his books on Cordova-Rios, Lamb, a native Coloradoan, collected family stories about Harvey Logan, alias Kid Curry, a member of the Wild Bunch, who visited the family ranch. Lamb published a book on the life of Kid Curry as well as an annotated bibliography on the Wild Bunch.
Scope and Content
The collection contains Lamb’s work as a forester; including maps, photographs, and research materials on his dissertation on mahogany, as well as correspondence, reports, maps, photographs and articles from his professional travels. The collection also includes drafts, notes, correspondence, and research files about Manuel Cordova-Rios and the Amazon; Kid Curry and the Wild Bunch; and Lamb’s unpublished book on ecology. Personal materials like daily calendars, notebooks, passports and travel documents, and employment records are also included.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by F. Bruce Lamb at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from F. Bruce Lamb 1971-1992, Elizabeth Lamb (wife) 1993-1996, and John Lamb (brother) 1995.
Access Terms
Cordova-Rios, Manuel, 1887-1978.; Logan, Harvey, ca.1867-ca.1910.;; Forests and forestry.; Outlaws -- West (U.S.); Cashinawa Indians.; Rubber industry and trade -- Brazil.; Mahogany.
Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Forestry and Forestry Products; People, Ethnicity, and Culture; Social Life and Customs
Container List
- Series I. Personal, 1930-1993
  Arranged alphabetically. Contains personal calendars, notes, employment records, and passports, and other travel documents; Graduation programs for the University of Michigan, and obituaries and memorial service information.
  - Address Book, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: University of Wyoming, American Heritage Center, 1973-1988 (Box 2)
  - Daily Calendars, 1949-1950, 1963-1974 (Box 1)
  - Daily Calendar for trips, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Daily Calendars, 1976-1987 (Box 2)
  - Employment Record and Applications, 1953-1967 (Box 2)
  - Employment Record, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Field Notes, 1945, 1951-1957 (Box 1)
  - The Harbinger, Lamar Union High School Yearbook, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Calendar, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries and Memorial Service Information, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Passports, Tourist Card, and Vaccination Certificates, 1966-1976, 1969, 1962-1978 (Box 2)
  - Reconstruction Fianance Corporation Certificate of Appreciation, 1945 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan, Graduation Programs, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan, 50th Reunion Classmate Information, 1991 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Plywood Corporation/Champion International Employee Benefit and Stock Option Information, 1963-1975 (Box 2)
- Series II. Professional Work and Research, 1938-1988
  Primarily reports, surveys, maps, memos, photogrpahs, pertinent correspondence, and printed materials regarding Lamb’s forestry assignments. Materials are grouped by country or company as arranged by Lamb. The arrangement was maintained, and material is listed alphabetically within each sub-series.
  - Sub-series 1. Rubber Development Corporation, 1942-1977
    - Articles on the Rio Tapajos written by Lamb, 1950, undated (Box 4)
    - Bibliography of Amazon Resources, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Calendars and Notes, 1942-1943, 1946, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 4)
    - Field Reports on Rubber Production in Brazil, 1942-1945 (Box 4)
    - List of Field Technicians, First Aid Information, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - List of Field Technicians and correspondence between them, 1944-1977 (Box 4)
    - Manuscript: E.B. Hamill, "Borracha", A Story of Amazon Rubber Production during WWII, undated (Box 4)
    - Maps of South America, 1940s (Box 4)
    - Photographs: Brazil, Rio Purus, Rio Tapajos, and Manaus, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - Photographs: Brazil, Rio Jurua, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - Photographs: Brazil, Rio Tapajos, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - Specimen Collection Notes, 1942-1960 (Box 4)
    - Trip Itineraires with notes, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
  - Sub-series 2. Puerto Rico, 1945-1948
    - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 4)
    - Memos on lumber procurement, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Reports on wood utilization in Puerto Rico, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
    - Report on Central America with pertinent correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Sub-series 3. Study of Mahogany, 1938-1972
    - Annotated Bibliography of Mahogany by Lamb (One Spanish Copy), 1959 (Box 5)
    - Articles and Correspondence on Philippine Mahogany, 1961-1966 (Box 5)
    - Article: C.D. Mell, "Biography of the word Mahogany", 1930 (Box 22)
    - Book: Lamb, Mahogany of Tropical America, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Book Reviews for Mahogany of Tropical America, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence: Publication of Dissertation on Mahogany, 1953-1959 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence: Travel Grant, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - Mahogany Literary Survey by Lamb, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Mahogany Research Materials: Articles, Newspaper Clippings, Notes, and Correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous: Charts, Copies of Photos, and Maps on Mahogany, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes and Drafts of 'Further Defining Mahogany', 1954-1958, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes and Correspondence on the Etymology of Mahogany, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Photographs: Logging, Guatemala, Panama, Bolivia, 1942-1943, 1952, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Publications by Lamb on Mahogany: Articles, 1954-1967 (Box 5)
    - Research Materials on Mahogany Etymology, 1947, 1965, undated (Box 5)
    - Travel Grants: Miscellaneous, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Sub-series 4. Guatemala, 1938-1987
    - Contract with Department of Forestry for Developing Industrial Forestry Units in Peten, Guatemala, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Memos on Forest Survey of Guatemala, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 4)
    - Extracts from Forests of Guatemala (In Spanish), 1950 (Box 4)
    - Guatemala, Final Report on forests with maps, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Guatemala, Survey and data findings for final report, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - Memo on Pulp and Paper Industry in Guatemala, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Photographs: Aerial, Peten, Guatemala, 1938 (Box 5)
    - Photographs: Miscellaneuos South America, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - List of Latin American Forestry Students who studied at University of Michigan, undated (Box 4)
    - Report: Timber Exploitation in Central America, 1890-1950, with correspondence, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Reports and Correspondence: Primavera Plantation Study, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Report on Road Construction in Peten, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Study, Reports, and Draft of Law for Developing Industrial Forestry Units in Peten, Guatemala, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Sub-series 5. Panama, 1945-1959
    - Articles on Panama, 1952-1953 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: Preliminary to assignment in Panama, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: International Cooperation Administration assignment to survey forets of Panama, 1956-1958 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: Publication of Report on Panama Forests in Yale Journal, Tropical Woods, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Itinerary Reports, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Maps of Panama, 1945, undated (Box 6)
    - Memo: Canal Zone Forestry Project, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Paper: R.W. Hess, "The Possiblities of Tropical Hardwood Production", undated (Box 6)
    - Reports: Forest Resources, Surveys, and Utilization of Timber, 1947-1958 (Box 6)
    - Speech: 'Utilization of the Forest Resources of Panama' to the Panama Rotary Club, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Sub-series 6. Colombia, 1951-1962
    - Article on Cimitarra, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, Correspondence: Preliminary to assignment with the Colombian Insitute of Colonization and Immigration, 1953 (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1954-1959 (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, Institute of Colonization and Immigration Magazine, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, Letter reporting on the Institute of Colonization Timber Utilization Program, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, List of Woods found in the Carare Region, undated (Box 6)
    - Cimitarra, Reports: Utilization Program, Carare Region soil, wood, and sawmill production, and industrial woods of Colombia, 1953-1954, undated (Box 6)
    - Container Company Report and correspondence with supporting documents, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: General Forestry consulting, 1953-1962 (Box 6)
    - Tumaco, Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 6)
    - Tumaco, Correspondence and draft of article on Colombian forests, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Tumaco, Maps, 1951, undated (Box 6)
    - Tumaco, Memo to Natomas Company, 1956 (Box 6)
    - Tumaco, Report: Timber surveys, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
  - Sub-series 7. Institute of Tropical Forestry, 1943-1988
    - Annual Letters, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
    - Book: The Forests of Costa Rica, U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1943 (Box 6)
    - Book: Badillo, Monografia de la Familia Caricaeae (In Spanish), 1971 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: Preliminary to assignment, 1959-1962 (Box 6)
    - Information Booklet, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Mahogany Hybred Photographs and distribution maps, undated (Box 6)
    - Report: Forest Plantation Survey of Mexico, Central America, Colombia, Ecuador, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Research Papers, 1960-1977 (Box 6)
  - Sub-series 8. U.S. Plywood Corporation, 1951-1984
    - Afris Bois, Congo-Brazzaville: Investigation with maps, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Congo, Africa: Reports, Surveys, Photographs, 1955-1957, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence: Prior to employment with U.S. Plywood Corp., 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence: General, 1962-1963 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
    - Daniel Ludwig's Jari Project, Brazil: Surveys, Reports, Memos, Correspndence, Newspaper Clippings and Photographs, 1966-1984 (Box 7)
    - Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) of the United Nations Documents, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Forest Resource Management Planning: Reports, Memos, Documents, 1955-1975 (Box 3)
    - Iquitos, Peru Veneer Mill: Reports, Charts, Photographs, Correspondence., 1963-1973 (Box 7)
    - Ivory Coast, Africa: Reports and Memos, 1966-1974 (Box 8)
    - Jari Project Gmelina Report, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Long-term Forest Resource Planning: Reports, Summaries, Memos, Correspondence, and Articles, 1959-1975 (Box 9)
    - New Peruvian Forestry Law, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Nigeria, Africa: Reports and Memos, 1964-1971 (Box 8)
    - Performas: Veneer Plant Operations, 1960-1969 (Box 8)
    - Reports - American Tropical Woods, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Reports: Forest and wood product resources, 1967-1974 (Box 9)
    - Reports: British and French Giuana forest surveys, timber and wood pulp studies, 1958-1970 (Box 7)
    - Reports: Nicaraguan pine and Eucalyptus plantation program in Brazil, 1970-1973 (Box 7)
    - Reports: Forest surveys and inspections in Columbia, Ecuador, Guatemala, Peru, Southeast Asia, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
    - Rio Jari - Amazon Timber Survey, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Russia: Correspondence, Memos, Summaries, and Articles on forest resourses, 1962-1974 (Box 9)
    - Sixth World Forestry Congress Documents, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Southeast Asia: Thailand, Philippines, Indonesia; Reports, Correspondence, Memos, 1962-1974 (Box 8)
    - Southeast Asia: Report on the Far East, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Trip Itineraires, 1943-1961, 1957-1962 (Box 3)
    - West Coast Reforestation: Memos and Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 9)
    - World forest resource use and projections, 1971 (Box 9)
  - Sub-series 9. Maps, 1948-1967
    - Aeronautical Charts: South America, New Guinea, Indonesia, Borneo, Philippines, Belgian Congo, 1948-1963 (Box 3)
    - Operational Navigation Charts: South America, New Guinea, Indonesia, Brunei, Africa, 1961-1967 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous maps of South America, undated (Box 22)
    - Various maps of South America, undated (Box 23)
  - Sub-series 10. Photographs, Negatives and Slides, 1956-1971
    - Film, Color: Yellowstone National Park, 1971 (Box 24)
    - Film, Color: Unidentified, 1970 (Box 24)
    - Photographs and Negatives: Jari and Iquitos, Brazil, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives: Manuel Cordova-Rios, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives: Columbia, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs: Joyce Kilmer Memorial forest and Teton National Park, 1971, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs: South America and Africa, 1950s, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Photographs: Peru, 1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs: Peter Mahogany Road, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives: Guatemala, circa 1956 (Box 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives: Philippines, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs: Unidentified, undated (Box 2)
    - Slides: Unidentified, Undated (Box 2)
    - Slides: Amazon and Manuel Cordova-Rios, 1967, undated (Box 2)
- Series III. Publications and Writings, 1939-1994
  Drafts, research materials including newspaper clippings, articles, and printed materials, in addition to correspondence for published and unpublished articles and books written by Lamb.
  - Sub-series 1. Articles, 1948-1991
    Articles topically cover forestry, environmental and ecology issues, reactions and defense of “Wizard of the Upper Amazon”, and articles on Kid Curry and the Wild Bunch. Correspondence and any drafts are grouped with the published article. Articles are arranged chronologically.
    - Articles: Includes corresponding correspondence and/or drafts, 1948-1991, undated (Box 10)
    - Chronological list of Publications, undated (Box 10)
  - Sub-series 2. Wizard of the Upper Amazon: The Story of Manuel Cordova-Rios, 1959-1988
    - Articles and Newspaper Clippings regarding the Amazon, 1959-1979 (Box 11)
    - Author's First Proof, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Author's Second Proof, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Bibliography index cards, undated (Box 11)
    - Book: Wizard of the Upper Amazon: The Story of Manuel Cordova-Rios, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Book: Wizard of the Upper Amazon: The Story of Manuel Cordova-Rios, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Book Reviews, 1971-1975 (Box 11)
    - Book Reviews, 1971-1975 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence: Manuel Cordova-Rios (In Spanish), 1962, undated (Box 12)
    - Correspondence: Potential publishers, Lamb's literary agent, readers, and those assisting in editing the book, 1968-1975 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence: Lamb's response to R.L. Carneiro's blast of Wizard book, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence: "Wizard of the Upper Amazon" and "Rio Tigre and Beyond", 1968-1983 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence: Rafael Pereira-Rios in Peru and an article on Manuel Cordova-Rios (In Spanish), 1982-1986 (Box 12)
    - Drafts of "Wizard of the Upper Amazon", undated, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Early Draft of "Wizard of the Upper Amazon", undated (Box 12)
    - Letters, articles, and draft of the "The Wizard Controversy", 1963, 1980, undated (Box 12)
    - Notes on Cordova-Rios and Spanish descriptions of the book, 1969 (Box 12)
    - Notebooks of notes (2), undated (Box 11)
    - Sections translated into Spanish, undated (Box 12)
    - Spanish articles on Manuel Cordova-Rios, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
    - Revisions for second edition, 1974-1975 (Box 12)
    - Revised draft of "Wizard of the Upper Amazon: Authentic or Fake Ethnography", 1988 (Box 12)
    - Various Notes and Revisions, undated (Box 11)
  - Sub-series 3. Rio Tigre and Beyond: The Amazon Jungle Medicine of Manuel Cordova, 1939-1992
    - Articles and Newspaper Clippings: Medicine, Alternative Medicine, Peru, Folklore, Drugs, The Amazon, 1945-1982 (Box 14)
    - Book: Rio Tigre and Beyond: The Amazon Jungle Medicine of Manuel Cordova, (2 copies), 1985 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews of "Rio Tigre and Beyond" and an article on Lamb, 1988; 1975-1976 (Box 14)
    - Chapter drafts, undated (Box 13)
    - Correspondence and draft of response to Timothy White's review of "Rio Tigre and Beyond", 1986 (Box 12)
    - Drafts of "Rio Tigre and Beyond" in various stages of revision, undated, 1975 (Box 13)
    - Drafts of "Rio Tigre and Beyond", undated, 1973-1975 (Box 14)
    - Incomplete Draft of "Rio Tigre and Beyond", 1973 (Box 13)
    - Manuel Cordova-Rios medical cases, (In Spanish), undated (Box 14)
    - Medical Cases of Cordova-Dios for "Rio Tigre and Beyond" and newspaper clippings on medicine, 1972; 1963,1978 (Box 13)
    - Periodicals, Newspaper Clippings, and Articles on Medicine, Alternative Medicine, Shamanism, and the Mind, 1964-1992 (Box 19)
    - Photographs of Manuel Cordova-Rios and Peruvians, 1943, undated (Box 13)
    - Reports and glossary of Tropical Plants, 1939-1944 (Box 14)
  - Sub-series 4. Kid Curry: The Life and Times of Harvey Logan and the Wild Bunch, 1948-1991
    - Article: "Sand Gulch" sent to Titsch Publishing, unpublished, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Article: "Piece of Tail at Robbers Roost" sent The New Yorker, unpublished, undated (Box 17)
    - Article: "Shootout at Turkey Creek", 1978 (Box 17)
    - Article: "Shootout at Turkey Creek" and correspondence with Montana Historical Society about publishing, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 17)
    - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1986-1991 (Box 17)
    - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1948-1975 (Box 17)
    - Book: Kid Curry: The Life and Times of Harvey Logan and the Wild Bunch, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Book Catalogues, 1969-1970, undated (Box 17)
    - Calendar Art, Maps, Article, Newspaper Clippings, Booklets, 1963-1989 (Box 17)
    - Calendar Art and Postcards of western scenes, 1974-1976 (Box 17)
    - Copy of "The Bandit Invincible" by William T. Phillips, 1986 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence regarding publication, 1990-1991 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence on research, 1971-1975 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence from Martha Adams, 1969-1970 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence with Daniel Buck and Anne Meadows in reference to their work on Butch Cassidy with copies of their articles, 1987-1989 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence (2 folders), 1988-1991 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence and writing from F. R. Lamb, 1948-1969, 1980 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence: Research, 1966-1979 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence seeking info on life of Curry, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Hand written sections of Kid Curry (2 folders), 1970-1975 (Box 15)
    - Hand written draft of Kid Curry (2 folders), 1976 (Box 15)
    - Draft: "Kid Curry: Life with the Wild Bunch", 1977 (Box 15)
    - Draft: "Kid Curry: Life with the Wild Bunch" (3 Folders), 1977 (Box 15)
    - Draft: "Kid Curry: Life with the Wild Bunch" (9 folders), 1981 (Box 15)
    - Draft with revisions, undated (Box 15)
    - Drafts, Revisions, and Notes by F. R. Lamb for his book, Wild Bunch, undated (Box 17)
    - Draft: Kid Curry pages 143-541 only (2 folders), undated (Box 16)
    - Draft: "Harvey Logan Alias Kid Curry: A Cowboy-Bandit's Life and Times", undated (Box 16)
    - Draft: "Harvey Logan Alias Kid Curry: A Cowboy-Bandit's Life and Times" (2 folders), undated (Box 16)
    - Draft: "Harvey Logan Alias Kid Curry: A Cowboy-Bandit's Life and Times", undated (Box 16)
    - Draft: "Kid Curry: Life with the Wild Bunch" (3 folders), undated (Box 16)
    - Final Draft of "Kid Curry: Life with the Wild Bunch" (3 folders), 1990 (Box 16)
    - Index Cards for Kid Curry book, undated (Box 16)
    - Index, bibliography, and copies of photos, undated (Box 17)
    - Letters seeking photos of Hite and Trachyte Canyon, Utah and other spots, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
    - List of expenses and receipts for writing 'Kid Curry' and 'Ecology not Ecocide', 1969-1970 (Box 17)
    - Map, Notes, Letters, 1971-1977 (Box 17)
    - National Geographic, featuring cowboy articles, 1971, 1976 (Box 17)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1959-1977 (Box 17)
    - Newspaper clippings on Hole-in-the-Wall Gang 75th Anniversity, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Notes and writing by F. R. Lamb on Kid Curry, circa 1940s (Box 17)
    - Notes, Articles, Maps, Bibliography on research, 1970-1974 (Box 17)
    - Notes and Timelines of Kid Curry activities, undated (Box 17)
    - Outline, synopsis, and acknowledgements for Kid Curry, undated (Box 17)
    - Reproduction Wanted Poster, Kid Curry, undated (Box 22)
    - Research Notes (3 folders), 1971-1990 (Box 17)
    - Research Notes and Microfilm Printouts, 1970-1971 (Box 17)
    - Research notes (2 folders), undated (Box 15)
    - Research notes on Knoxville, TN, undated (Box 17)
    - Reviews and Press, 1991 (Box 17)
  - Sub-series 5. The Wild Bunch: A Selected Critical Annotated Bibliography of the Literature, 1992-1994
    - Book: 'The Wild Bunch: A Selected Critical Annotated Bibliography of the Literature', 1993 (Box 16)
    - Draft: "The Wild Bunch Bibliography", 1992 (Box 16)
    - Draft: "The Wild Bunch Annotated Bibliography", 1992-1993 (Box 16)
  - Sub-series 6. Kidnapped in the Amazon Jungle, 1986-1994
    - Book: Kidnapped in the Amazon Jungle, 1994 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence and sample draft of "Amazon Jungle Adventurer", 1986 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence: "Kidnapped in the Amazon", 1989-1992 (Box 12)
    - Drafts: "Kidnapped in the Amazon Jungle: The Adventure of Manuel Cordova-Rios", 1992, undated (Box 12)
  - Sub-series 7. Ecology Not Ecocide: A Long Way from Cotopaxi, A personal view of the Changing Landscape of Ecology, 1967-1975
    - Book: Ecotactics: The Sierra Club Handbook for Environment Activists, Edited by John G. Mitchell and Constance L. Stallings, 1970 (Box 19)
    - Book: Voices for the Wilderness, Edited by William Schwartz, 1969 (Box 19)
    - Book: Wilderness and the American Mind, by Roderick Nash, 1969 (Box 19)
    - Chapter revisions, 1971, undated (Box 19)
    - Drafts: "Ecology Not Ecocide: A Long Way from Cotopaxi, A personal view of the Changing Landscape of Ecology", 1971, 1972 (Box 18)
    - Draft: 'Ecology Not Ecocide', undated (Box 19)
    - Periodicals, Newspaper Clippings, and Articles on Ecology and Enviromental Issues, 1967-1975 (Box 18)
    - Photographs and slides of clearcutting, undated (Box 18)
  - Sub-series 8. Correspondence, 1949-1994
    - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1946, undated (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1949-1972 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence: Readers Digest, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Dorothy Kamen-Kaye, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Commentary on Lambs books, 1982-1991 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Research topics, 1987-1994 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: W.S. Merwin's poem, 'The Real World of Manuel Cordova', 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Botanical Musuem of Harvard University, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1971-1983 (Box 3)